{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In a 1910 toast, John Collins Bossidy called this city “the land of the bean and the cod.” Abolitionist sentiment surged in this city when William Lloyd Garrison founded The Liberator newsletter there. Despite the anti-Catholic sentiment of its founders, this city became a center of Irish-Catholic politics. Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr. wrote about this city’s so-called “Brahmin” elite. For ten points, name this major New England city, nicknamed “Beantown.”",
      "answer": "Boston, Massachusetts"
    },
    {
      "question": "A participant in this conflict named Rodrigo Diaz briefly switched sides after the Battle of Cabra and had a nickname meaning “the Lord.” Jews who did not flee this conflict were forced to become “conversos.” This event’s unofficial end came in 1492, when the Emirate of Granada fell to Spanish forces under the control of married Christian monarchs. For ten points, give the Spanish-language term for the expulsion of Muslims from Spain, led by Ferdinand and Isabella.",
      "answer": "Reconquista"
    },
    {
      "question": "John Walter Bratton composed a song about a picnic held by these objects. A trip with Governor Andrew Longino inspired these items, which were exported to the US in the 55 PB form by Alban Berg's brother, Hermann. Morris Michtom and Richard Steiff created these toys which were inspired by a Clifford Berryman cartoon showing a hunter refusing to kill a tied up animal with the words \"Drawing the Line in Mississippi.” For ten points, name these stuffed toys named for Theodore Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "Teddy Bears"
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1885 rebellion resulted in this polity’s reorganization under its first premier, Sir Frederick W.A.G. Haultain. Originally, this polity’s official language was French, though English became the official language in 1892 after a decisive vote by the Confederation Government in Ottawa. In 1999, this polity ceded land for the creation of its neighboring territory of Nunavut. For ten points, name this most-populous of the three Canadian federal territories, whose capital is Yellowknife.",
      "answer": "Northwest Territories"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jules Ferry blasted the 19th-century redesign of this city as “triumphant vulgarity,” while other critics noted that wider streets could be used in this city to more easily maneuver troops to counter uprisings. A series of glass and iron pavilions were built at this city’s central marketplace of Les Halles [[layz-ALL]]. Marc Chagall was hired to repaint the ceiling of a Charles Garnier-designed opera house in this city. Napoleon III hired Baron Haussman to renovate, for ten points, what city on the Seine River?",
      "answer": "Paris"
    },
    {
      "question": "President Bill Clinton called this event a “terrible sin” and mourned the 6 children killed during this event. One perpetrator of this event was apprehended as a result of a routine traffic stop. That man, and another named Terry Nichols, were inspired to carry out this event by the ATF siege at Waco. The weapon used in this attack was a rented Ryder truck. For ten points, name this terrorist attack on the Alfred P. Murrah building perpetrated by Timothy McVeigh.",
      "answer": [
        "Oklahoma City Bombing",
        "similar answers for “Bombing” such as “Attack”,",
        "answers that indicate the attack on the Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Belief in this location may have been inspired by the healing of a paralyzed man at Bethesda, as recounted in the Gospel of John. The Arawak people believed this location to be in the mythical land of Bimini. One explorer, Juan de Solís, placed Bimini in the Gulf of Honduras, whereas the best known searcher of this location thought it to be in the Bahamas. For ten points, name this fabled body of water, for which Juan Ponce de León supposedly searched in Florida.",
      "answer": "Fountain of Youth"
    },
    {
      "question": "As Communist Party First Secretary in Sverdlovsk, this man carried out orders to tear down the house where the Romanovs were killed. This man became a non-voting member of the Politburo in 1986 after Mikhail Gorbachev appointed him mayor of Moscow. This man’s visit to a Houston, Texas grocery store in 1989 is suspected to have contributed to the downfall of the Soviet Union. For ten points, name this political dissident and first President of the Russian Federation.",
      "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nash Motors operated out of this city, where AMC also manufactured the Renault Alliance. Joseph Rosenbaum and Anthony Huber were killed in this city, while Gaige Grosskreutz was injured, leading to Dominick Black's arrest. A 17-year old from Antioch, Illinois, Kyle Rittenhouse, illegally used his rifle in this city. Officer Rusten Sheskey stopped an SUV in this city, then shot Jacob Blake seven times. For ten points, name this Wisconsin city, a center of racial unrest in the US in late 2020.",
      "answer": "Kenosha, Wisconsin 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person’s 1766 appearance before Parliament helped convince the British government to repeal the Stamp Act. This man’s son was the last colonial governor of New Jersey. Harry Meanwell and Silence Dogood are just two of this author’s many aliases. This man improved the catheter, invented the glass harmonica, and founded the University of Pennsylvania. For ten points, name this “First American,” famous for his kite experiment and Poor Richard’s Almanac.",
      "answer": "Benjamin Franklin 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Sarah Hopkins Bradford wrote a biography of this person who was the victim of a gold transfer swindle by John Thomas. This woman's mother, Rit, defended her family from Edward Brodess, and this woman developed hypersomnia when an overseer threw a metal weight at her head. This person helped Colonel James Montgomery scout out Jacksonville, Florida and aided Montgomery in the Combahee River Raid. For ten points, name this Underground Railroad conductor, who was called \"Moses.”",
        "answer": "Harriet Tubman"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tubman has been proposed to replace President Andrew Jackson who has been featured since 1928 on this US currency denomination.",
        "answer": "$20 bill"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ancient sources called these people the Raeti, and the English words \"military\" and \"person\" are thought to come from the language of these people. These people created impasto pottery and may have come from the Villanovan culture. These people created the Tomb of the Blue Demons and the Tomb of the Leopard. Tarquinius Superbus came from these people, and Emperor Claudius wrote a history of them. For ten points, name these ancient Italians whom the Romans displaced.",
        "answer": "Etruscans Civilization"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Etruscan league, or Dodecapolis, was founded by Tarchon and another man who gives his name to this sea, an arm of the Mediterranean that is bounded by Corsica and Sardinia.",
        "answer": "Tyrrhenian Sea"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This plant is damaged by microscopic cyst nematodes as well as the ten-striped spearman in the Rocky Mountains. Copper pesticide can control the Phytophthora infestans disease from damaging this plant. Monsanto genetically engineered the New Leaf form of this plant of which Chuno is a freeze fried version. These plants were first domesticated in Peru and Bolivia and widely replaced turnip and rutabaga production. For ten points, name this crop, the subject of a Great Famine in Ireland in the mid-19th century.",
        "answer": "Potato"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the Potato Blight returned again in 1879, an agrarian movement had begun fighting for this resource. A series of acts over this resource occurred after an 1879 war named for it in which tenants tried to take this resource.",
        "answer": "Land 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These two countries engaged over the Chumbi Valley in the Nathu La and Cho La Clashes over the Kingdom of Sikkim. These two countries disputed borders along the McMahon Line and the Line of Actual Control. In order to avoid war over Tibet, these two countries codified the Five principles of Peaceful Coexistence. Fighting over the Aksai Chin, these two countries clashed over the Forward Policy on the Himalayan border in a 1962 war. Led by Nehru and Mao, for ten points, name these two most populous countries in the world.",
        "answer": "People's Republic of China and the Republic of India"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "China and India have disputed water rights on the Brahmaputra River that flows from high in the Himalayas into this river, the third largest in the world in terms of total discharge.",
        "answer": [
          "Ganges River",
          "Ganga River"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Seeichi Kito and Donald Jung are among those who claim to have created these items. The largest manufacturer of these items, headquartered in Brooklyn, creates more than 4.5 million of them per day. That company, Wonton Food, unsuccessfully attempted to market these items in China. First served in the United States at the Japanese Tea Garden in San Francisco, for ten points, name these items made from flour, sugar, and vanilla, typically containing a memorable expression or a potential future event on a slip of paper.",
        "answer": "Fortune cookie"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The ubiquitous paper take-out box found in US Chinese restaurants is named for this bivalve mollusk as the boxes were used by fisherman in the early-20th century. Jonathan Swift said, \"He was a bold man who first ate\" one of these creatures.",
        "answer": "Oyster"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This king captured 120 standards, today found at Riddarholm Church. Finnish troops serving under this man were called Hakkapelitta or \"Cut them down!\" Lennart Torestensson helped this man catch the Tercios of the Count of Tilly. Gustav Horn served this ruler, who rode the war horse Streiff without wearing armor and was killed in the fog at Lützen [[LOOH-tzen]]. This man won at the Battles of Lech and Breitenfeld in the Thirty Years' War. For ten points, name this Vasa king of Sweden.",
        "answer": [
          "Gustavus Adolphus",
          "Gustav II Adolph"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This daughter of Gustavus Adolphus abdicated her throne in 1654 when she converted to Catholicism and is one of the few women buried in the Vatican grotto.",
        "answer": "Christina, Queen of Sweden 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, an association called Honest People reported thousands of election violations. In 2006, this country's OMON police tried to stop one candidate from campaigning. This country's current president won 80% of all votes in the 2020 election, defeating Sviatlana Tsikhanouskaya [[tsik-on-oo-SKY-ah]]. The Coordination Council attempted to take power away from this country's leader, nicknamed \"Europe's Last Dictator.\" For ten points, name this Eastern European country in which people protested against Alexander Lukashenko in Minsk.",
        "answer": "Republic of Belarus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2006, the democratic opposition in Belarus led this revolution against the election of Lukashenko, named for a blue-colored clothing.",
        "answer": [
          "Jeans Revolution",
          "Denim Revolution",
          "or Cornflower Revolution"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The conditions at this battle, featured in the opening scenes of the Academy Award winning 1989 film Glory, were described by one soldier as “almost impossible for a rat to live in.” Some of the earliest fighting at this 1862 battle swirled around Dunker Church. Burnside’s Bridge and Bloody Lane are landmarks at this site, where Robert E. Lee’s first invasion of the North was stopped cold. For ten points, name this battle that occurred on the single bloodiest day of the US Civil War.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Antietam",
          "Sharpsburg"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Democratic nominee in the 1864 presidential election was removed from his command of the Army of the Potomac, in part due to his tactical error in failing to pursue the Confederate Army after the Battle of Antietam.",
        "answer": "George B. McClellan"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Great Smoky Mountains",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Long hiking trail completed in 1937, 70 miles of which are in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park.",
          "answer": "Appalachian Trail"
        },
        {
          "question": "UN organization that designated the region a World Heritage site in 1983.",
          "answer": "UNESCO or United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization"
        },
        {
          "question": "New Deal president who opened the park in 1934.",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR,"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Side most Great Smoky Mountains residents supported in the Civil War despite being in the South.",
          "answer": [
            "Union",
            "answers indicating the U.S. Federal government"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Forced relocation march that Great Smoky Mountain Cherokee residents underwent.",
          "answer": "Trail of Tears"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conquistador, the first European to cross the Mississippi, who spent time in the Chiaha village.",
          "answer": "Hernando de Soto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Culture which lived in the Mountains and built mound cities like Cahokia.",
          "answer": "Mississippian Culture"
        },
        {
          "question": "Highest point in the Mountains nicknamed for North Carolina's \"Prince of Politicians.\"",
          "answer": "Clingmans Dome 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Rise of Nazism",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Alcoholic beverage that names a failed “Putsch” by the Nazis.",
          "answer": [
            "Beer",
            "Beer Hall Putsch"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Book written by Adolf Hitler while in prison, outlining his ideology.",
          "answer": [
            "Mein Kampf",
            "My Struggle"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German Parliament building set on fire by a Dutch communist.",
          "answer": "Reichstag"
        },
        {
          "question": "Elite Nazi unit who killed political opponents in the “Night of the Long Knives.\"",
          "answer": [
            "SS",
            "Schutzstaffel"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "World War One hero whose weak presidency allowed the Nazis to suspend civil liberties.",
          "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-Semitic paper published by Julius Streicher which spread Nazi propaganda.",
          "answer": [
            "Der Sturmer",
            "The Stormer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Gay leader of the SA and member of the Nazi “Old Guard,” executed during the “Night of the Long Knives.”",
          "answer": "Ernst Röhm"
        },
        {
          "question": "1933 Act which gave Hitler the power to circumvent the president and his cabinet.",
          "answer": "Enabling Act 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Costa Rica",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Southern neighbor to which it lost Chiriqui, featuring a canal.",
          "answer": "Republic of Panama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island nation with which it broke diplomatic ties in order to recognize the PRC.",
          "answer": [
            "Taiwan or Republic of China,",
            "Formosa,"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Yellow fruit that Minor C. Keith grew for Chiquita and United Fruit.",
          "answer": "Banana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital which contains the Barrio Amón.",
          "answer": "San Jose"
        },
        {
          "question": "Primary export sold by the Barons, known for its arabica form.",
          "answer": "Coffee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Action José Figueres Ferrer took toward the military after winning the civil war in 1948.",
          "answer": [
            "Eliminated it",
            "similar descriptive answers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Plantations, larger than estancias, that failed due to lack of Encomienda labor.",
          "answer": "Haciendas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Drummer boy who died at the Second Battle of Rivas for whom the primary airport is named.",
          "answer": "Juan Santamaría 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1996, this man's campaign ran ads warning voters to \"Get BeSheared.” In his first senatorial election, this man narrowly defeated Walter Dee Huddleston. This man controversially called the Families First Coronavirus Response Act an \"ideological wish list.\" This man's (20 pts)",
        "wife, Elaine Chao, served as Secretary of Transportation in the Trump administration. This man blocked the hearings for Merrick (10 pts)",
        "Garland as Senate Majority Leader. For ten points, name this Kentucky senator and Senate Minority Leader as of January, 2021."
      ],
      "answer": "Mitch McConnell"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "The lives of these people in Rome and Classical Antiquity was studied by J. P. V. D Balsdon and Sarah Pomeroy. In Ancient Greece, these people did not live in the andron, but instead were reserved for the gynaeceum. Unmarried people of this kind formed the (*) \"Basket Bearers\" or Kanephoros. In Athens, the right of these people to sign contracts was restricted, though they had large (*) dowries. For ten points, name these people who, in Aristophanes's play Lysistrata, fought their husbands."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Women",
        "Wives and similar answers specifically indicating females"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this year, a sitting US president visited Cuba for the first time in 95 years. Writers Elie Wiesel [[EE-lee vee-ZEL]] and Harper Lee died in this year as did hockey great Gordie Howe, whose June death occurred on a palindrome day. In January of this year, the World (20 pts)",
        "Health Organization reported that the Zika virus was spreading rapidly through the Americas. The World Series winner in this year broke the 108-year (10 pts)",
        "Chicago Cubs curse. For ten points, identify the year in which Barack Obama visited Cuba and endorsed Hillary Clinton for president."
      ],
      "answer": "2016"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this conflict, the pincer movement was utilized in battle for the first time. After a large discovery of silver during this conflict, one side created 200 triremes that fought at Artemisium. One of the early phases of this war was the Ionian (20 pts)",
        "Revolt, and other battles fought during this conflict include the battles of Thermopylae [[ther-MAH-puh-lee]] and (10 pts)",
        "Marathon. For ten points, name this conflict, one side of which was led by men including Darius and Xerxes against a number of smaller city-states centered on the Balkan peninsula."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Greco-Persian Wars",
        "obvious equivalents,",
        "Battle of Marathon before “silver” 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hurley Medical Center led two studies on this event, including one by Mona Hanna-Attisha. LeeAnne Walters won the Goldman Prize for her advocacy during this event. Mayor Dayne Walling lost to Karen Weaver following this event, which occurred after a contract with the (20 pts)",
        "Karegnondi Water Authority. Rick Snyder declared a state of emergency during this event in Genesee County. This event involved the release of corrosive (10 pts)",
        "lead from pipes sourced from the Detroit River. For ten points, name this public health crisis in Michigan."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Flint Water Crisis",
        "descriptive answers of the water crisis in Flint"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the Middle Ages, this man was the only commander on record using \"feigned retreat,” such as at the Battle of Amblève. Ragenfrid and Chilperic II were defeated by this man at Vinchy. Dagobert III's son, Theuderic IV, had his reign controlled by this man who was himself the son of (20 pts)",
        "Pepin of Herstal. This man was jailed by Plectrude in Cologne, the site of his only defeat. This man defeated Abdul Rahman Al-Ghafiqi and the Umayyads at (10 pts)",
        "Tours. For ten points, name this Frankish ruler, known as \"the Hammer.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Martel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Glenn and William Sewell built one of these devices using erector pieces. Vladimir Demikhov made the first of these devices, one of which Henry Optik received from General Motors Research. In Houston, Michael DeBakey worked with one of these devices called an LVAD. Willem Johan Kolff and Robert (20 pts)",
        "Jarvik worked on the development of these devices, one of which was implanted in dentist Barney Clark who lived 112 (10 pts)",
        "days afterwards. SynCardia is an example of, for ten points, what type of device that replaces a blood pumping organ?"
      ],
      "answer": "Artificial heart"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man declared that “Education is the key to opportunity in our society” and signed a bill doubling federal spending on education. A namesake Texas law he helped pass allowed this man to win reelection to the US Senate and the Vice Presidency in the (20 pts)",
        "same election. Three years following that election, this 36th US president became the first to be sworn in by a (10 pts)",
        "woman, doing so while aboard Air Force One in 1963. For ten points, name this man who took office following the assassination of John F. Kennedy."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Lyndon Baines Johnson",
        "LBJ,"
      ]
    }
  ]
}